Yep.
好的。
Hey buddy, people hear what I'm saying.
嘿，大家能听到我说话吗？
You're good, good.
很好，能听到。
Awesome, I just want to get started with similar to last week
好的，我想像上周一样开始，
where we asked you about, the util lab,
上周，我们问了一些 util 实验的问题，
I just want to get started by asking a little bit about syscall lab,
我想先问一下 syscall 实验的情况，
since that was due on Thursday.
因为那是周四到期的。
So if anybody just has like something particularly interesting, they found about the lab
所以如果有人在实验中发现什么特别有趣的东西
or a nasty bug that they found
或者发现一个难缠的 bug ，
or just a silly mistake they made,
或者只是犯了一个愚蠢的错误，
anything you want to share about the syscall lab to be， [that'd be great.]
关于 syscall 实验，任何你想分享的都可以。
I somehow managed to delete the part from where from fork where you have to copy over the mask,
不知道什么原因，我删除了 fork 中需要通过 mask 复制的部分，
so I had that working and then I change something else and then I tested it for.
我让它工作，然后我修改了其他东西，然后我测试它，
Your audio is like cutting out.
你好像掉线了。
Oh, it is sorry, you hear me.
哦，抱歉，你能听到我说话吗？
I hear you.
我听到了。
Oh, okay.
好的。
Yeah I guess.
我想是的。
So basically I deleted somehow the copy of the mask
基本上我以某种方式删除了 mask 的复制，
and then my my fork didn't work anymore,
然后我的 fork 就不能用了，
so then I was just like I did that, how does it not work,
所以我想，之前还是好的，现在怎么不能用了，
so spend a lot of time figuring out. What I did wrong.
我花了很多时间去找问题。
And I realized I just deleted that line from the.
我意识到我把那行删除了。
Is anybody having trouble hearing Luca, is that on my end.
有没有人听不到 Luca ，还是只有我这边。
I think its on your end.
我想只是你那边。
Yeah I'm fine.
是的，我这边是好的。
This must be on my end.
那一定是我这边的问题。
Sorry, maybe that'll work better now.
抱歉，现在应该好了。
Can you hear me now, okay great.
现在能听到我说话吗？好的。
I was worried that I was just talking.
我还担心我这边。
No, no, seems to be on my end.
不，好像是我这边的问题。
Alright.
好的。
Awesome, will anybody else have anything they'd like to share about you of syscall.
好的，还有人想分享关于 syscall 的任何事情吗？
Anything particularly interesting,
有什么特别有趣的，
or was the lab absolutely horrendous
或者实验太难了，
and you think we should cut it out of the class, never do it again.
你觉得我们应该把它从课程中删掉，再也不做了。
I have something, apparently the order of things matters which is a general statement,
我有一些东西，概括来说，事情的顺序很重要，
so I tried to determine the mass computation inside the syscall function.
我试着理解 syscall 函数内的代码，
Before determining whether I actually needed to do the tracing.
在理解之前，我需要先做 tracing 。
And so all the syscall we're getting correctly traced except that trace call.
所有系统调用都能正确跟踪，除了 trace call 。
And I was really getting disturbed by that,
这件事让我心烦意乱，
until I think it was David who pointed out,
直到 David 指出，
you know you should do the computation after [you should trace] just like that's fun.
你知道，应该在 trace 之后进行计算。
Alright. I'm glad you were able to catch that.
好的，很高兴你能找到这一点。
Yeah order does matter,
是的，顺序确实很重要，
especially for page tables, you'll find I think that order matters there as well
特别是对页表来说，你们会发现，顺序在那里也很重要，
and generally throughout the class, paying attention to the order of things will be important.
而且贯穿整个课程，注意事物的顺序很重要。
It's good to not overwrite things in page table.
最好不要覆盖页表中的内容。
I also had something which I'm actually still confused about.
我也有一些东西，事实上我现在仍然对此感到困惑。
Well I had a lot of debugging print statements in the kernel code.
我在调试内核代码时用了很多 print 语句。
I then ran that trace thing with all of the bits set,
然后我把所有的位都设置好，运行 trace ，
so basically tracing all the system calls.
基本上跟踪了所有的系统调用。
And, I think I saw a lot of tracing for the print statements in the kernel, and then.
我看到了内核中很多 print 语句的跟踪，然后。
Because and then I assumed that my print my print apps were trying to read and write to the console,
然后我假设我的 print 程序读取和写入控制台，
but that do write to the console,
确实会写入控制台，
but then I was wondering why are we.
但我想知道是为什么。
I guess, I'm just confused why we're able to use printf in the kernel.
我想，我困惑的是，为什么可以在内核中使用 printf 。
Yeah I'm not I haven't looked at the printf code recently,
我最近没有看过 printf 的代码，
but I think there's a file printf.c
但是我想有一个 printf.c 文件，
you might be a look at if you want to.
你可以自己看一下。
Um, here what was going on there,
嗯，这里发生了什么，
so I think the printf function should be [implemented in there].
我认为 printf 函数是在那里实现的。
At least our version of it,
至少我们的版本是这样的，
I don't know perhaps one of the what are some of the other core staff might know what's going on.
我不知道，或许其他工作人员可能知道是怎么回事。
And the printf in the kernel shouldn't show up as your traces,
在跟踪的时候，内核中的 printf 不应该出现，
because printf in the kernel doesn't call any system calls.
因为内核中的 printf 不做任何系统调用。
Yeah that's what I thought,
是的，我也是这么想的，
maybe that maybe the tracing was not from that.
也许 tracing 不是从那里来的。
Yeah I don't think it is from your printf in the kernel.
是的，我不认为它来自内核中的 printf 。
Okay.
好的。
OK, well unless anybody has any other burning comments about syscall,
好的，除非还有人对 syscall 有别的评论，
I think we can get started with lecture for today.
我想我们可以开始今天的讲座了。
I'll be talking a little bit about the process of converting C to assembly and processors,
我将谈谈 C 语言转换为汇编语言的过程和处理器，
and this is more of a practical lecture today
今天更多是一个实用的讲座，
or at least that's the aim,
至少这是我们的目标。
so the goal here is to get you all familiarized with RISC-V
我们的目标是让你们熟悉 RISC-V ，
the processor, the assembly language and calling conventions for RISC-V.
熟悉它的处理器、汇编语言和调用约定。
And this will be important,
这是非常重要的，
in not not super important for page table,
虽然对页表来说不是特别重要，
but certainly for the traps lab which is will be assigned later this week,
但是对于这周布置的的 traps 实验来说是这样的。
this will be essential for debugging and implementing things,
对于调试和实现都是必不可少的，
because you'll be working quite intimately with trap frame and stack and things like that,
因为你将直接使用 trap frame 和堆栈之类的东西，
so that's the that's kind of the goal for today.
所以这就是今天的目标。
And, my first aim was to,
我的第一个目标是，
this might be a little bit of review from 6.004
这是对 6.004 课程的一点回顾，
or any other computer architecture theme classes that you may have taken in the past,
或者你学过的任何其他计算机体系结构课程。
but I just want to go over briefly kind of see
我只想简单回顾一下，
the C language, how we get to assembly
C 语言是如何转换成汇编语言的，
and I'm maybe a little bit about processor.
还有一点处理器相关的知识。
So, throughout, and then of course throughout this lecture,
当然，在这节课的整个过程中，
feel free to interrupt with any questions that you have.
如果你有任何问题，可以随时打断我并提问。
So, you know, we have our normal main functions in C.
你知道，在 C 程序中，一般都有 main 函数。
You know they do something, maybe they print something, then they exit.
它们会做一些事情，也许是打印一些东西，然后退出。
And this all looks well and good,
这些看起来都很好，
but as any of you are aware from 6.004
但正如你们从 6.004 知道的，
processors don't actually understand the C language,
处理器实际上并不理解 C 语言，
rather they understand what we call a assembly
它们理解的是我们称为汇编的东西，
or more specifically they understand the binary encoding of assembly,
或者更具体地说，它们理解的是汇编的二进制编码，
and so this here I've circled a picture of
这里我在照片中圈出来的
an actual RISC-V processor from a SiFive board,
是 SiFive 板上真正的 RISC-V 处理器。
and when we say a processor is RISC-V
而且当我们说处理器是 RISC-V 时，
that means that it understands the RISC-V instruction set,
意思是它可以理解 RISC-V 指令集，
so every processor has an associated ISA or instruction.
每个处理器都有关联的 ISA 或指令。
And that's kind of the set of instructions,
那就是一套指令集。
that makes sense to that processor,
对处理器来说是可以理解的，
so every instruction has an associated binary encoding or an op code.
每条指令都有相关的二进制编码或操作码。
And when a processor is running
当处理器运行时，
and it sees a particular encoding, it knows what to do.
会看到一种特殊的编码，然后知道该怎么做。
And so, you know this processor on this board happens to understand the RISC-V assembly
所以，你知道这块板上的处理器理解 RISC-V 汇编，
which is what C code is compiled to,
汇编从 C 代码编译而来，
so the general process of getting C code to actually run on your processor is,
所以让 C 代码真正在处理器上运行的一般过程是，
we start with C, it gets compiled to assembly,
编写 C 代码，然后编程成汇编语言，
and there's some linking and things like that happened between this step
这之间还发生了一些链接之类的事情，
but that's we are not a compiler class,
不过我们不是一门编译器课程，
so and then the assembly will then be translated into binary,
然后汇编语言会被翻译成二进制。
and so this is the object or .o files that you see.
这就是我们看到的 obj 或 .o 文件。
so if you've ever paid attention to what's inside of your lab directory after you run make qemu,
如果你在运行 make qemu 之后注意过实验目录中的内容，
you'll see a bunch of .o files lying around
你会看到很多 .o 文件散落在各处，
and those are the actual object files that the processor understands.
这些就是处理器能够理解的目标文件。
And the asm files, you've also seen,
你们也看到了 asm 文件，
you haven't really written any, but if you recall from syscall,
你还没有写过任何汇编代码，但是如果你回想 syscall ，
usys.pl is compiled to a file called usys.S
usys.pl 文件被编译成 usys.S ，
and so .S files are assembly language,
而 .S 文件就是汇编，
and so you've seen you've certainly seen some RISC-V assembly
所以你肯定已经到了一些 RISC-V 汇编
and if you took 6.004
如果你学过 6.004 ，
I believe you've also seen a good amount of assembly language.
我相信你也看到过很多汇编代码。
An assembly looks in general much less structured than C,
一般来说，汇编看起来比 C 语言的结构化程度要低得多，
so you'll just see line after line after line of instructions,
你会看到一行接一行的指令，
you'll see simple things like add mult etc, and so on and so forth,
你会看到一些简单的东西，比如 add mult 等。
and this doesn't have no nice control flow, there's no loops,
它也没有好的控制流，没有循环语句，
there are functions but not in the sense that you might remember from C,
有函数，但不是 C 语言那种函数，
we see labels as opposed to true function definitions.
我们看到的是标签，而不是真正的函数定义。
And the assembly, so it's a much lower language
汇编语言，是一种低级语言，
and there are plenty of other languages that are also compiled to assembly,
还有很多其他语言可以编译成汇编语言，
so, the same process holds true for things like C++.
比如，同样的过程也适用于 C++ 。
Um, you know any any language that's compiled
嗯，你知道任何一种编译语言，
will go to the same assembly language at the base.
最终生成相同的汇编语言。
And, so that's kind of the basic process of
这就是运行的基本过程，
getting our computer to actually understand the C code that we're writing,
计算机真正理解我们编写的 C 代码，
but you'll notice that we've been referring to RISC-V assembly.
但要注意，我们指的是 RISC-V 汇编。
Throughout the course and the processor is RISC-V
在整个课程中，处理器都是 RISC-V ，
and that's because, it it's important because there's many different kinds of assembly,
这很重要是因为有许多不同类型的汇编，
so it's unlikely that you're using RISC-V yourself,
你可能不会自己使用 RISC-V ，
like you're not going to be running Linux on it,
比如你不会在上面运行 Linux ，
instead most modern computers will run on what's called x86 or you'll sometimes see is x86-64.
相反，大多数现代计算机在 x86 上运行，或者有时候看到的 x86-64 。
And this is this is a different ISA, this is a different instruction set,
这是一个不同的 ISA ，不同的指令集，
it looks pretty similar to RISC-V,
它看起来与 RISC-V 很像，
but this is what you see in kind of your personal computers often.
但这是你经常在个人电脑上看到的。
So if you use an Intel
所以，如果你使用英特尔处理器，
so Intel CPU's implement x86 and I believe AMD also do.
英特尔 CPU 实现了 x86 ，还有 AMD 。
And [this is] relatively important distinction between the two,
这是两者之间相对重要的区别，
they're not quite as similar as they may look at first
它们并不像看起来那么类似，
and that comes down to the fact that RISC-V is what we call as a RISC,
这归结于一个事实， RISC-V 是我们所说的 RISC ，
the RISC part of RISC-V refers to a reduced instruction set.
RISC-V 的 RISC 部分指的是精简指令集。
And x86-64 is what's called a CISC or complex instructions.
而 x86-64 是所谓的 CISC 或复杂指令集。
And there's a couple of key differences here,
这里有几个关键的不同之处，
one is just the number of instructions that are present in x86-64,
其中之一就是 x86-64 中存在的指令数量，
in fact one of the big motivations for writing, for for making RISC-V was
事实上，创建 RISC-V 的动机之一就是
how many instructions we actually have.
我们实际上有多少指令。
In the Intel kind of handbook, so for reference, there's three full books,
在英特尔手册里，有三本完整的书可供参考。
that encompass the ISA and some statistics,
包括 ISA 和一些统计数据，
I think there's new instructions have been added at a rate of three instructions per month.
新的指令仍然以每月三个指令的速度增加。
Since x86-64 was added, it was first published in the seventies,
自从 x86-64 发布，它最早是在七十年代发布的，
so I believe there's like north of 15,000 instructions in x86-64.
大概有 15000 多条指令在 x86-64 中。
And RISC-V on the other hand,
而 RISC-V 则相反，
the assembly for RISC-V can be nicely contained within two documents.
RISC-V 的程序集可以包含在两个文档中。
And so, a kind of going off of that,
某种程度上，
we don't expect you in this course to memorize every single RISC-V instruction,
在这门课上，我们不需要你们记住 RISC-V 的每一条指令，
but if you are interested
但是如果你感兴趣，
or you ever find yourself confused by what a specific instruction is or does,
或者发现哪条指令自己不清楚，
if you go to the course website
如果你访问课程网站，
and we look under the references tab,
我们可以在 references 菜单下看到，
under RISC-V we give you the links to both the privileged and unprivileged instruction sets,
在 RISC-V 下，我们提供了特权指令和非特权指令集的链接，
so this is kind of the document that gives you a whole bunch of information about the ISA,
这个文档给出了很多关于 ISA 的信息，
but you'll note that like this is 240 pages, and this is 135 pages,
但是注意，这个有 240 页，这个有 135 页，
so it's significantly significantly smaller than the x86 instruction set,
所以它比 x86 指令集小得多，
that's one of the nice things about, about RISC-V,
这是 RISC-V 的优点之一，
so we have in RISC-V we have fewer instructions
因此，在 RISC-V 中，我们的指令更少，
and not only that, the instructions are simpler.
而且指令更简单。
So, what I mean by that is that,
所以，我的意思是，
there are many instructions in x86-64 by,
在 x86-64 中有许多指令，
for example, that referring to something like add or mul sub.
比如，有 add mul sub 等。
In x86-64 there's plenty of instructions, that do more than one thing,
在 x86-64 中，有很多指令不仅做一件事，
so they perform some complicated set of operations and then gets you the result
它们会执行一些复杂的操作，然后给出结果，
and that's not the case with RISC-V RISC-V instructions tend to be smaller in scope,
而 RISC-V 则不同，指令的范围往往较小，
and so they take less cycles to run each instruction then maybe x86-64 is
比 x86-64 用更小的周期来运行每条指令，
and this is just a trade-off that the designers chose to chose to undertake.
这只是设计者选择的一种权衡。
There's nothing or you know there's no canonical reason
没有什么规范的理由，
why I reduced instruction set is better than you know a complex induction instruction set,
为什么精简指令集比复杂指令集好，
they each have their own uses, and so on and so forth
它们各有其用途，
and another cool thing about RISC-V as opposed to x86 is that, this is open source,
与 x86 相比， RISC-V 还有一个很酷的地方，就是它是开源的，
so one of the only open source instruction sets on the market,
是市面上仅有的开源指令集之一，
so that means anybody can develop a board for RISC-V
这意味着任何人都可以为 RISC-V 开发电路板，
and it came out of a research project from UC Berkeley
它来自加州大学伯克利分校的一个研究项目，
and so that's kind of where was RISC-V started
这就是 RISC-V 开始的地方，
and since then it's been picked up and supported by a number of companies,
从那时起，它得到了很多公司的支持，
you can find the list online,
你可以在网上找到这个列表，
but yeah there's tons of big companies that are interested in supporting an open instruction set.
确实有很多大公司对支持开放指令集感兴趣。
And actually I think quite recently there was an announcement made by SiFive
事实上，最近 SiFive 开了一场发布会，
who are sort of the premier board manufacturer for RISC-V processors,
他们是 RISC-V 处理器的首屈一指的电路板制造商，
that they will be releasing a board for personal computers
他们将发布一款适用于个人电脑的电路板，
that should extensively a RISC-V processor designed to run Linux for personal computers
该板将采用 RISC-V 处理器，为了在个人电脑上运行 Linux ，
and I think that's been released in the last week or two, the announcement about it.
我记得是在过去一两周开的发布会。
So if you're if you're curious if your find yourself
如果你很好奇，如果你发现自己，
you know absolutely I want to use RISC-V after I finish 6.S081,
你知道，我在完成 6.S081 之后，很想使用 RISC-V ，
hopefully by that time there will be a processor available
希望到那时候有处理器可用，
that you can run Linux on your own computer.
可以在自己的计算机上运行 Linux 。
But even in your day-to-day lives,
但是即使在日常生活中，
you're most likely using reduced instruction set even if you don't realize it,
你也很可能使用了精简指令集，可能你没有意识到这一点，
so the ARM assembly, so that's A R M,
所以 ARM 指令集， A R M ，
this is also a reduced instruction set。
也是精简指令集。
And ARM is implemented by Qualcomm, the the snapdragon series of processors.
高通公司实现的 ARM 是骁龙系列处理器。
So if you have an android phone, you are most likely running a reduced instruction set.
所以，如果你有一部安卓手机，很可能运行的是精简指令集。
And even if you're using ios, ios I think I forget what the name of it,
即使你用的是 iOS ，我忘了叫什么，
but Apple has some has some version of ARM,
但是苹果也有一些版本的 ARM ，
they also implement in their own processors
他们也在自己的处理器上实现了，
that runs on ipads iphones and most mobile Apple devices,
这些处理器运行在 iPad iPhone 和多数苹果的移动设备上，
so reduced instruction sets are present all over the place,
所以精简指令集随处可见，
and if you're looking for a RISC-V in the real world,
如果你在现实世界中寻找 RISC-V ，
you know outside of your QEMU
你知道，在 QEMU 之外，
you'll be able to find that in like integrated devices.
你可以在集成设备中找到它。
So it is present, it's not as certainly not as ubiquitous as something like x86-64
所以它是存在的，虽然不想 x86-64 那样广泛，
but it's um.
但它是。
Yes I yes I think Apple is as Lucas just said I think Apple is moving Mac to ARM.
是的，就像 Luca 刚才说的，苹果正在将 Mac 转向 ARM 。
I believe that's also the case,
我相信情况也是如此，
there's been in last year's definitely been a push towards reduced instruction sets.
去年确实有一股精简指令集的热潮。
Given given how big the Intel ISA has gotten.
英特尔指令集为什么这么大？
And the reason why Intel ISA is so big is because
英特尔指令集这么大的原因是，
they're very concerned with backwards compatibility.
因为他们非常关心向后兼容性。
So if you write.
所以如果你写了。
A modern Intel processor can run the same instructions
一个现代英特尔处理器
that Intel code from you know 30 40 years ago was was written,
也可以运行三十四年前编写的指令，
it so they don't really deprecate any instructions so that they maintain backwards compatibility,
他们不弃用任何指令，以保证向后兼容性，
that RISC-V is more modern, so it's not a worry RISC-V is.
RISC-V 更现代，所以不需要考虑这个。
Also if we jump back to those manuals,
如果我们回到那些手册，
RISC-V is unique in that it's divided,
RISC-V 的独特之处是它的指令是分开的，
we have what's called the base integer instruction set which all RISC-V processors, um.
所有的 RISC-V 处理器都有基本整型指令集。
If we have fifteen.
如果我们有。
Gabriel asks in the chat,
Gabriel 在聊天中问道，
if we have 15,000 instructions, it nearly impossible to efficiently pipeline them,
如果有 15000 条指令，几乎不可能有效地使用它们，
why do we need so many.
那么为什么需要这么多。
Like I was saying we need so many for backwards compatibility reasons,
就像我说的，需要这么多指令，是出于向后兼容的原因，
it's up to you to decide you know whether you think that's super important.
这是由你自己决定的，你是否认为这是非常重要的。
But many of those instructions I think a ton of them are also [] by simply instructions
但是我想很多指令被简单的指令所[]，
which are their own kind of special class of things.
这是它们特有的东西。
You won't I I I've never seen
我从没见过
Intel assembly code that makes full uses full usage out of the 15,000 instructions,
英特尔汇编代码能充分利用这 15000 条指令，
but mostly this comes from a from a need for backwards compatibility and simply.
这主要是出于向后兼容的需要，并且保持简单。
But like I was saying the RISC-V has a what's called the base integer instruction set,
就像我说的， RISC-V 有一个基本整型指令集，
which contains all of the normal add multiply things,
它包含所有正常的加法、乘法运算，
and then processors can choose to implement a number of other modules,
然后处理器可以选择实现其他模块，
which you can see along the side here,
你可以在这边看到，
it's probably impossible to read on your screen,
可能你在屏幕上看不清楚，
but for example if you want a processor,
举个例子，如果你希望处理器
you know that supports standard extension for single precision floating point,
支持单精度浮点型标准扩展，
then you can include the F module.
你就可以包含 F 模块。
And this makes it easier for RISC-V to support backwards compatibility,
这使得 RISC-V 更容易支持向后兼容，
because if, you can just say what set of modules do I include and support
因为你可以指出包含和支持哪些模块，
and the compiler can choose.
而编译器可以选择。
Then, compiler can say okay, you know this processor is telling me it supports these modules,
然后，编译器告诉我它支持这些模块，
so I can only compile this code with these modules.
所以我可以用这些模块编译这段代码。
Okay, Bibik says
好的， Bibik 说，
it seems that the only advantage of using x86 instead of RISC-V processor
似乎使用 x86 而不是 RISC-V 处理器的唯一优势是
is the kind of performance you can get,
可以获得更好的性能，
however, that performance comes as a massive cost and complexity and potential security,
然而，这种性能是以巨大的成本、复杂度和潜在的安全性为代价的，
my question is why are we still using x86,
我的问题是为什么我们还在使用 x86 ，
instead of moving to something like RISC-V.
而不是转向 RISC-V 。
Well, a big answer that the world is run on x86,
好的，一个宽泛的答案是，世界运行在 x86 之上，
for I I don't have a great answer for why.
我也没有一个更好的答案。
RISC-V is pretty modern too.
RISC-V 是相当现代的，
So the world as a whole pretty much runs on x86,
世界几乎都运行在 x86 上，
so if you suddenly start converting your processors to RISC-V,
如果突然把处理器转换为 RISC-V ，
you run the risk of, you know losing support for a bunch of important things,
你会冒着失去对一些重要事情支持的风险。
also there are like Intel does do interesting things within their processors,
另外，英特尔在他们的处理器中也做了一些有趣的事情，
like security wise, there are enclaves on Intel processors
比如在安全方面，有 enclave ，
and there's things that they've been doing in recent years
而且近年来他们一直在做一些事情，
to try to try and give you extra added security
试图提供额外的安全性，
and some of those instructions that Intel does implement
英特尔确实实现了一些指令，
which are hyper specific can be really efficient for certain, computations.
这些指令对某些特定的计算是非常有效的。
And so they have so many instructions,
所以他们有这么多指令，
there's often you know, a perfect instruction for a situation
你知道，多数情况下，一种情况对应一条指令，
that may be more efficient than then what exists within RISC-V,
这可能比 RISC-V 更有效。
but a more practical answer is
但一个更实际的答案是，
at RISC-V is relatively new
RISC-V 相对较新，
and we just don't know, nobody's really making processors for personal computers,
还没有真正为个人电脑制造的处理器，
I think the SiFive announcement is super recent,
SiFive 的发布会是最近举办的，
and they're kind of the first people to be doing that.
他们可以说是第一批这样做的人。
so on a practical level, that and the inability to run all the software design for Intel
所以在实践上，不能运行所有为英特尔设计的软件，
is is my best answer.
这是我最好的答案。
So we've been now chatting a little bit about assembly,
我们现在讲一下汇编，
so I just wanted to take a look at some actual assembly code.
我想先看一些实际的汇编代码。
So here is the C code for what's below,
这是一段 C 代码，
so this is a simple function that has an accumulator,
有一个简单的函数，一个累加器，
we loop from zero to n
我们从 0 循环到 n ，
and we sum up all the numbers from from zero to n,
然后将 0 到 n 的所有数字加起来，
and then return that value.
然后返回这个值。
And at its simplest level, this is the easiest kind of assembly,
这是最简单的级别，最简单的汇编代码，
you can get out of compiling that program,
你可以编译这段程序，
if you actually go into your own computer and you write the C code and you try to compile it,
如果你真的编写了 C 代码，并编译它，
you will end up with something that likely looks quite different.
你可能会得到一些看起来完全不同的东西。
And that's true for a variety of reasons,
这是正确的，有不同的原因，
we have a some of which we'll get to and some of which are compiler specific,
我们会看到其中一些原因，还有一些是特定编译器的，
so modern compilers make a large number of optimization,
现代编译器进行了大量的优化，
With it when they compile your C to assembly,
当使用编译器将 C 编译成汇编时，
and so your assembly instructions may look different,
所以你的汇编指令看起来可能会不同，
for instance while you're debugging in gdb
例如，当你在 gdb 中调试时，
you may come across something that tells you that it's some variable has been optimized out,
可能会遇到一些东西告诉你某个变量已经被优化，
and that means that the compiler decided it didn't need that variable
意思是编译器决定不需要该变量，
and so that'll be gone effectively from the program,
因此，这个变量会从程序中消失。
but yeah and it's at its most straightforward, we're moving value that's in a0 the t0,
这是很直接的，我们把 a0 中的值移动到 t0 ，
we're setting a0 to zero
我们把 a0 设置为 0 ，
and then we are just adding what's in t0 to a0,
然后把 t0 中的内容加到 a0 上，
for every iteration of a loop until t0 reaches zero.
对循环中的每次迭代，直到 t0 变为 0 。
And that's all that's going on in this piece.
这就是这段代码的意思。
Amir, your hands raised.
Amir, 你举手了。
I was wondering what .section .text .global do.
我想知道 .section .text .global 是做什么的。
A global means that you can include this from other files,
global 表示你可以从其他文件中包含这个，
so if we actually hop into, let's see defs.h.
如果我们去看，看一下 defs.h 。
This is the file that you're will, if you aren't already, you will become quite familiar with,
这是你后面会非常熟悉的文件，
this includes basically all of the functions within the kernel that you may want to be using
包含内核中可能使用的所有函数
and within here you know we can see that,
在这里，我们可以看到，
in my my file, I've included the definitions to these functions,
在我的文件中，已经包含了这些函数的定义，
and so that .global makes sure that, that these these functions can be called from other places
这样， .global 保证这些函数可以从其他地方调用，
and .text just says this is code.
而 .text 表示这是代码。
So if you recall from figure 3.4 in the book,
如果你回想一下书中的图 3.4 ，
so that's if we go to the book,
我们去看那本书，
and we go into page tables process address space,
我们进入页表进程地址空间，
so in here in this diagram, that's the same thing is text, so just means code.
在这张图中，这和 text 是一样的，表示代码。
That answer your question?
这回答了你的问题吗？
Thanks.
谢谢。
And so if we want to run, um.
如果我们想运行，嗯。
Let's say we have some assembly,
我们有一些汇编代码，
also if you ever find yourself interested in what the kernel looks like,
如果你发现自己对内核代码感兴趣，
we can go inside the, after you compile you can look in the file kernel/kernel.asm.
我们可以进入，编译后你可以查看 kernel/kernel.asm 文件。
And this is the full kind of assembly for the kernel of xv6,
这是 xv6 内核的完整汇编代码，
and each of these numbers on the left here is a label
左边的每个数字都是一个标签，
that tells you where in memory, this in this instruction will be
告诉你这个指令在内存中的位置，
and that will come in quite handy.
这是很有用的。
And so here is the here's the actual,
所以，这就是实际的，
use the actual assembly code and you can see the labels for the functions and whether declared,
使用实际的汇编代码，你可以看到函数的标签以及声明，
so this is this is, can be really really useful as we're debugging code
这在我们调试代码时是非常有用的，
and hopefully I'll be able to show that in a second.
稍后我将展示这一点。
But for now we'll jump back to this first function, sum_to
但是现在我们回到第一个函数 sum_to ，
and we'll just see how we can examine that inside of gdb,
我们看看如何在 gdb 中调试，
so the first step is I have my two windows here.
第一步，这里我有两个窗口，
What's the difference between .asm .S files?
.asm 和 .S 文件有什么不同？
Um, not a hundred percent certain,
嗯，我也不是很确定，
they're both assembly,
它们都是汇编，
I think the .asm file includes a bunch of extra annotations that aren't included in .S,
我想 .asm 文件包含了许多 .S 文件没有包含的额外注释，
so usually when you compile your c code to .S,
通常情况下，你把 C 代码编译成 .S 时，
you'll end up with something that doesn't include all those line numbers and things like that.
你会得到一些不包含行号的汇编代码，
So, if you're curious about how we get asm file,
如果你想知道如何获得 .asm 文件，
I think the makefile will tell you the exact steps used to get that.
我想 makefile 会告诉你获得它的准确步骤。
And so if we're in our terminal, we have our two two windows,
我们回到终端，我们有两个窗口，
so the first thing to do is of course get QEMU up and running.
首先要做的当然是启动并运行 QEMU 。
So gdb, started within gdb mode,
在 gdb 模式下启动，
so now we're frozen here and then we can start gdb,
现在我们卡在这里，然后我们启动 gdb 。
and what what what what professor Frans showed last week.
就像 Frans 教授上周展示的那样。
Which I think some people were excited,
我想有些人会很兴奋，
you typed UI, enable you get this nice window
输入 tui enable ，会出现一个窗口，
which is empty for now but will come in quite useful as you're debugging,
现在是空的，但在你调试时会很有用，
so we can set a break point
我们可以设置一个断点，
and I should note that all this code is living inside the kernel, none of this is in user space,
应该注意到这些代码都在内核中，没有一个在用户空间，
so we don't have any of those annoying problems setting break points,
所以我们设置断点时没有什么烦人的问题，
so I can set a break point in the function sum_to and then just continue running.
我可以在函数 sum_to 设置一个断点，然后继续运行。
Run that function and now, so the first window that you see in tui is the source window.
现在运行该函数，你在 tui 中看到的第一个窗口是源码窗口，
Yes, as David is saying those those numbers on the left of kernel .asm are really useful
是的，像 David 说的， kernel.asm 左边的数字是非常有用的，
when you're debugging things and you get an address it'll tell you,
当你调试的时候，你得到一个地址，它会告诉你，
so you can see now,
所以你可以看到，
even here we can see that the programs of PC here in gdb, is the program counter,
我们可以在 gdb 中看到 PC ，即程序计数器，
so we can see this address eight zero zero so on and so forth.
我们可以看这个地址，以 800 开头的，
If we go into kernel.asm and we search for that specific address,
如果我们查看 kernel.asm ，并查找那个地址，
we can see that it's the,
我们可以看到它在，
um, it comes up twice because the function call,
嗯，它出现了两次，因为函数调用，
but if we look here, this is that address, it's the top of the sum_to function.
我们看这里，这就是那个地址，它是 sum_to 的开头。
So if you see any time you see one of these,
所以如果你在任何时候看到这些东西，
um all the kernel addresses will look something like a 0x8000 some numbers.
所有内核地址都是 0x8000 这样的数字。
Those addresses you can jump straight into kernel.asm
这些地址你可以直接跳转到 kernel.asm ，
and find the exact line of assembly where the problem is occurring,
并找到发生问题的那一行，
and then you can set your break points accordingly,
然后可以在相应地设置断点，
but for now, the top window in tui is source,
现在 tui 的顶部窗口是源码窗口，
and if we want to look at specifically the assembly we can do layout in gdb asm,
如果我们想要查看汇编，可以在 gdb 中输入 layout asm ，
and that'll give us all of the assembly instructions and,
这会给我们所有的汇编指令，
we can also look at the registers if we type layout reg,
如果我们输入 layout reg 还可以查看寄存器，
we'll get assembly and registers
我们得到汇编和寄存器，
and if you find yourself what to scroll through things,
如果你要浏览什么东西，
now that we have three windows, we need to specify which one is focused,
现在我们有三个窗口，需要指定聚焦在哪个窗口，
so if I want to look for all the registers, I'm going to focus reg.
如果我想查看所有的寄存器，输入 focus reg 。
And now my focus is on the register window
现在我聚焦在了寄存器窗口，
so I move the arrow keys or scroll you'll start scrolling that window.
这时移动箭头键或者滚动，就可以在那个窗口滚动了。
Now we can focus on the assembly window.
现在，我们聚焦在汇编窗口。
And once we're here, we can see all of the things,
我们到了这里，就可以看到所有的东西，
so let's see, we can see in the registry register window,
让我们看看，我们可以在寄存器窗口中看到，
we can see that t0 contains this value,
我们可以看到 t0 包含这个值，
we can see that a0 contains this value.
可以看到 a0 包含这个值。
And as we step through the assembly, we can watch,
当我们单步执行汇编时，可以看到，
say OK, t0 just got the value of a0 which was five,
t0 刚刚得到了 a0 的值，也就是 5 ，
and it's nicely highlighted the register that's changed.
它也高亮显示了发生改变的寄存器。
Here and we can just, keep remember if we push enter we get the most recently executed instructions,
这里我们可以，如果按下 enter 键，会得到最近执行的命令，
so we can go through, we set a0 to zero
我们继续，将 a0 设置为 0 ，
and now we can just kind of watch ourselves go through this loop and some of the values,
现在我们可以看到这个循环和其中一些值，
and then this is like a complete you know [] function.
这就像是一个完整的[]函数。
Then continue and live our lives
我们继续，
and if you're ever curious about what kind of break points you've set
如果你想知道设置了什么断点，
or you lose track of what you were doing,
或者忘记了你在做什么，
if you type info break or breakpoints,
输入 info break 或 breakpoints ，
you can see all of the break points that you set in your code,
就可以看到代码中设置的所有断点，
and you can even see okay, this break point has already been hit one time
你甚至可以看到，这个断点已经命中了一次，
and you get lots of useful information doing that.
这样你就能得到很多有用的信息。
If you don't want to have the register window, but you do want to look at the registers,
如果你不想使用寄存器窗口，但需要查看寄存器，
info reg or info registers or i registers
输入 info reg 或 info registers 或 i registers
or any of the numerous gdb shortenings will bring up the register window.
任何一个都可以调出寄存器窗口。
So with that is there any are there any questions about gdb?
那么，有关于 gdb 的问题吗？
Simple ones, I know it's been, there's been lots of post some [] about it,
简单的问题，我知道已经有很多关于它的[]了，
so now's a good time to just ask some straightforward,
所以现在可以问一些简单的问题。
well I'll be showing more usage as gdb.
我会展示更多 gdb 的用法。
What command did you use to open the multiple windows?
你使用什么命令打开多个窗口？
So I use tmux,
我使用的是 tmux ，
so I can show just from scratch,
我可以从头开始演示，
if we go here, I open a new terminal, so here's just a blank terminal.
在这里，我打开一个新的终端，只有一个空白的终端。
If you type tmux and this is available on Athena.
如果你输入 tmux ，在 Athena 上也是可用的。
Um, I'll answer the next question in a second,
嗯，我一会再回答下一个问题，
so now I'm in tmux, which you can tell by this green bar at the bottom
现在我在 tmux ，你可以从底部的绿色状态栏看出来，
and if you want to get so there's a couple ways you can do multiple windows in tmux,
在 tmux 中，有几种方式可以创建多个窗口，
if you're, so you can type control-b c
你可以输入 control-b c ，
and I know that sometimes if you're used to using emacs that will make a lot of sense,
如果你习惯使用 emacs ，对此会很熟悉，
but normal people who don't use emacs
但是对于不使用 emacs 的人，
that's hitting control and then b and then hitting c on its own afterwords,
就是先按下 control 键，然后按下 b ，然后单独按下 c ，
that will get you a second window
这会打开第二个窗口，
which you can then navigate between with control b and then p,
然后，你可以使用 control-b p 或
control b and n to go previous and next.
control-b n 在它们之间切换，
Yeah and David just posted that tmux cheatsheet which is useful
是的， David 刚刚贴出了 tmux 的 cheatsheet ，这很有用，
and if you want to split the windows,
如果你想拆分窗口，
I think it's control b and then the percent sign will split them, um, vertically,
使用 control-b % 会垂直拆分窗口，
and then sign a double control b and double quote will split them horizontally,
使用 control-b " 会水平拆分窗口，
and so that's how we get them.
这就是我如何得到它们的。
If we're in this state, we can use control b and o to jump between our windows,
如果我们处于这种状态，可以使用 control-b o 在窗口之间切换。
so that's that's how I got multiple windows.
这就是我有多个窗口的方法。
Yeah [].
是的，[]。
And then Ahmed asked why is displaying assembly addresses again instead of C line numbers.
Ahmed 问，为什么显示汇编地址，而不是 C 行号。
So because the function.
因为函数。
So if we go back to the assembly function,
如果我们回到汇编函数，
this is implemented entirely in assembly and not at all in C
这完全是由汇编语言实现的，而不是用 C ，
and so there just aren't any associated C line numbers for this.
所以没有与此相关的 C 行号。
If we were to set a break point,
如果我们要设置断点，
so if you type delete you will delete all your break points,
如果你输入 delete ，可以删除所有断点，
so I cleared the old one if I now set a break point in demo one,
我删除旧断点，现在在 demo_1 中设置一个断点，
so that's a C break point and continue and run this,
这是一个 C 断点，然后继续运行，
now if I go here and type layout split I'll get the C and the assembly.
现在，我输入 layout split ，会得到 C 和汇编窗口。
Um, or if I just want to C source, I can do layout source and I'll just get to C.
如果我只想要 C 源码窗口，可以使用 layout source ，然后就只有 C 。
So that's that's what's going on,
这就是正在发生的事，
it's just a quirk of the fact
基于这个事实，
that this doesn't have associated C code and so we don't see C line numbers.
它没有关联的 C 代码，所以看不到 C 行号。
Any other any other questions about gdb tmux, and that sort of thing.
关于 gdb tmux ，还有别的问题吗？
So layout split is the one that you use to
所以 layout split 用来
Yes yes, so layout if you do layout split that'll get you source and assembly,
是的，如果你使用 layout split ，可以得到源码和汇编窗口，
layout source will get you just source,
使用 layout source 只得到源码窗口，
asm will get you just assembly.
使用 layout asm 则只有汇编窗口。
And the registers are their own thing where you type layout, reg I think.
寄存器是单独的，你可以输入 layout reg ，
Yeah, that will bring up the registers,
是的，这会调出寄存器，
but unfortunately I don't know of a way
但是，我不知道有什么方法
to get to register the assembly and the C code all at the same time
可以同时调出寄存器、汇编和 C 源码。
outside of using info reg with layout split.
除了在 layout split 状态下使用 info reg 。
I have a question, so when we set the back breakpoint at line right.
我有一个问题，当我们在行中设置断点。
Um,
嗯，
it displays the address of the like in this case breakpoint to add to 0x80006354,
这种情况下，断点添加到类似 0x80006354 这样的地址，
what any instruction might have multiple, any line of code in C might have multiple instructions,
指令可能有多个， C 中的代码行可能有多个指令，
so which one does show.
那么显示的是哪一个？
I think it shows the first one.
我想显示的是第一个。
And it's tu-, for the person who asked to start tui,
对启动 tui 有问题的人，
it's I think it's tui enable, not enabled tui, sorry.
我想命令应该是 tui enable 而不是 enable tui ，不好意思。
And I think yeah.
我想是的。
Yeah.
是的。
Yeah again there's a hundred cheatsheets out here for gdb and for tmux,
是的，再提一下，这里有一些 gdb 和 tmux 的 cheatsheet ，
as well so if you ever find yourself lost.
如果你发现自己不会用，可以看一下。
I t-, gdb even has its own inbuilt it's own thing called apropos,
gdb 还有自己的内置手册，叫做 apropos ，
so if you look for apropos tui,
如果你输入 apropos tui ，
it'll actually show you all of the commands that involve tui.
它会显示所有相关的 tui 命令。
So yeah, this can be quite useful, but it can also be a little bit overwhelming.
是的，这可能非常有用，但也有点令人不知所措。
If you do apropos -v that it will give you even more information I think.
如果你使用 apropos -v ，它会给你提供更多信息。
Um I don't remember, I I don't use it often myself.
嗯，我不记得了，我不经常使用它。
But if you do find or if you forget the exact way to type the command in gdb
但是如果你要查找或忘记了 gdb 中输入命令的确切方式，
and you don't feel like google
而且你不想使用谷歌，
and apropos's will will often be able to find exactly what you're looking for,
apropos 能够找到你要找的东西，
in addition to a whole bunch of stuff you are looking for.
还包括很多关联的东西。
Yeah, so this is actually quite useful, gdb is extremely well documented as well,
是的，所以这是非常有用的， gdb 也有很好的文档。
so um, yeah, if you ever find yourself lost, you know, google is your friend.
所以，如果发现自己不会使用，你知道的，谷歌是你的朋友。
So now that we've kind of been over assembly and and RISC-V and these sort of things,
现在我们来看汇编和 RISC-V 以及相关的东西，
I want to dive a little bit more into the specifics
我想深入讲解一下细节，
of what you you really need to know for the lab coming up
你们在随后的实验中会用到，
and also it'll be a little bit of review from the document
另外，这也是对文档的一个回顾，
that you've of course, diligent students read through thoroughly in preparation for this lecture.
当然，我想勤奋的同学已经读过一遍了。
Um, so yeah, this table will of course be a wildly familiar to you all
是的，这张表你们很熟悉，
and from from both 6.004 and from what you've read,
从 6.004 或你们自己读的资料中，
and this is the table of registers
这是寄存器表，
and registers are little locations on the CPU around the processor predefined
寄存器是 CPU 上处理器周围预设的很小的位置，
that it can use to store values and this is important,
它可以存储值，这很重要，
because assembly operations if we remember from the assembly code,
因为汇编操作，如果你记得汇编代码，
the assembly doesn't operate on memory, it operates on register,
汇编不是在内存上操作，而是在寄存器上操作，
so when we do add when we do subtract we're operating on registers.
所以我们做加法、减法时，是在寄存器上操作。
And so what you often see as the pattern for writing assembly
所以你经常看到一种编写汇编的模式，
is will have some kind of a load, so we'll load some value to a register.
有一个 load ，将一些值加载到寄存器中。
And that value can be from memory, or it can be from another register.
这个值可以来自内存，也可以来自另一个寄存器。
And, and here referring to load in general, not the load instruction.
这里泛指加载，而不是 load 指令。
And then we'll operate, so we'll perform some operation on the register,
然后我们会操作，在寄存器上执行一些操作，
and then if we care about the result of that operation outside the return address,
如果我们关心返回地址之外的操作结果，
we will, we'll store that register to somewhere, to some locate,
我们可以把寄存器的值存储到某个地方，
they will store that register to some location in memory or to another register
将寄存器的值存储到内存中某个位置或另一个寄存器。
and that's generally the way things work
这就是通常的操作过程，
and registers are the absolute fastest way to perform any sort of calculation or to access any value
寄存器是执行任何计算或访问任何值的最快方式，
and that's why it's important to use them
这就是为什么使用它们很重要，
and also why we prefer using registers overusing memory,
也是我们更应该使用寄存器而不是内存的原因，
so if you remember from the reading when we call functions
如果你们记得文档中，我们调用函数时，
so you can see here that registers a0 to seven.
可以看到，寄存器从 a0 到 a7 。
And in general when we speak about registers we we will be referring to them by their ABI name,
一般来说，当我们谈到寄存器时，会使用它们的 ABI 名称来指代它们，
not only is it less confusing, it's just a standard
不仅减少了混淆，也是一个标准，
and it's also the way that you'll write assembly code,
也是你编写汇编代码的方式，
this, you know, these these actual numbers are not super important,
这个，这些实际的数字并不是特别重要，
the only case where it does matter is for the compressed version of RISC-V instructions
唯一有意义的情况是对于 RISC-V 指令的压缩版本，
and if you want to know more about that, feel free to read up about it,
如果你想了解更多，可以查看文档，
the basic idea is that RISC-V, normal instructions are 64 bits,
基本思想是 RISC-V ，普通指令是 64 位，
but there's also a compressed version, which instructions are sixteen bits
但是也有一个压缩版本，指令是 16 位，
and we use less registers and the registers we use in that case are eight through fifteen,
我们使用的寄存器更少，这种情况下，使用的寄存器是 8 到 15 ，
those are the registers that are available to us.
这些是我们可以使用的寄存器。
So I think somebody had a question about why is this s1 register x9,
有人提问，为什么这个 s1 寄存器 x9 ，
why is it, separated from all of the other's registers?
为什么它与其他所有寄存器分开？
And my guess is that that's why,
我猜是这样，
that we separated from all the other ones because it's available in compressed instruction mode,
我们把它与其他分开，因为它在压缩指令模式下是可用的，
whereas s2 to eleven or not.
而 s2 到 s11 不是。
And so that's the idea, that's that's a compress,
这是我的想法，它是一个压缩指令寄存器，
but outside of that register will be referred to by their ABI name
但是在寄存器之外，将通过它们的 ABI 名称来引用，
and so a0 to a7 are used for function arguments,
a0 到 a7 用于函数变量，
but if we have a function that takes
但是如果有一个函数接受的参数数量，
more than the eight arguments that those registers give us access to,
超过可以访问的寄存器数 8 个，
we do need to use memory
我们就需要内存，
but that's, this is kind of an illustration of the fact
但这在某种程度上也说明了一个事实，
that we don't want to use memory when we can use registers.
当我们可以使用寄存器时，就不使用内存。
We only we only use a memory, we have to.
我们只在必须的时候使用内存。
And this, this column here, the saver column,
这一栏， saver 栏，
this is also extremely important
也是非常重要的，
when we're discussing registers caller versus callee saved.
在我们讨论调用者（caller）和被调用者（callee）保存寄存器时，
And the terms are I confuse them regularly,
这两个属于我也经常混淆，
caller and callee, the only differ by one letter,
caller 和 callee 只有一个字母的区别，
the easiest way that I've found to remember them is
记住它们最简单的方法是，
that caller saved registers are not preserved, across a function call,
调用者保存寄存器在函数调用期间不会保留，
so and callee saved registers are preserved.
而被调用者保存寄存器会保留。
What I mean by this, is that,
我的意思是，
a caller saved register can be overwritten by the function,
调用者保存寄存器可以被函数重写，
so let's say I have function a which calls function b,
比如我有函数 a 调用函数 b ，
any registers being used by function a that are caller saved.
函数 a 使用的任何寄存器都是调用者保存的。
Call function b can overwrite when it gets called,
调用函数 b 可以在其被调用时覆盖，
and I think a good illustration of this is the return address.
我想返回地址（Return address）就是一个很好的例子。
Because you know you can see that the return addresses caller saved.
你可以看到返回地址是调用者保存的。
And that's important because every function needs to use the return address,
这一点很重要，因为每个函数都需要使用返回地址，
so when a calls b,
因此，当 a 调用 b 时，
it's important that b is able to overwrite the value in the return address,
b 能够覆盖返回地址中的值是很重要的，
hence why its caller saved.
这就是为什么它是调用者保存的。
And callee saved registers are just are convention that we use,
而被调用者保存寄存器只是我们使用的约定，
the frame pointer is important for that reason.
所以，帧指针（frame pointer, s0/fp）非常重要。
And those are preserved across function calls,
这些寄存器在函数调用之间保留，
so basically any register that is caller saved,
所以对于调用者保存寄存器，
the function that is making the call needs to worry about those registers,
进行调用的函数需要考虑这些寄存器，
and if they're callee saved,
如果是被调用者保存的，
the function that is being called needs to worry about preserving the value in those registers.
则被调用的函数需要考虑如何保存这些寄存器的值。
And again, you know I I regularly confuse the two
你知道，我经常混淆这两个，
and find myself returning to this table, to remind myself about what they do.
可以回到这张表，看看它们是怎么用的。
And so, You know you if you remember from the reading,
如果你记得读过的内容，
all of these registers are 64 bits wide,
所有这些寄存器都是 64 位的，
so they have 64 places where we can put things
所以，它们有 64 个位置可以放东西，
and the various data types are made to fit into those 64 bits based on the calling convention,
基于调用约定，各种类型数据适用于 64 位，
so if we have a 32 bit integer,
所以如果我们有一个 32 位整数，
depending on how it's whether or not it's an extended,
根据它是不是扩展的，
you know will either add zeros or ones to the front of that integer,
我们可以在它前面添加 0 或 1 ，
in order to make it 64 bits to put in these registers.
以便将其设置为 64 位放入这些寄存器。
So before we move on,
在我们继续之前，
does anybody have questions about registers or things of that nature.
有没有关于寄存器或相关的问题。
I have a question,
我有一个问题，
can you have a-, can you put a return value in a1.
能把一个返回值放在 a1 中吗？
Yes, that's a good question.
是的，这是个好问题。
So, I think in theory you can,
我想理论上是可以的，
the reason why we say a0 to a1 is
原因是，比如 a0 到 a1 是，
if a function returns a long long which is 128 bits,
如果函数返回 128 位的长整型，
so if you remember from the reading if a function argument is a hundred is more than a pointer-word.
如果你记得，如果一个函数参数是 100 ，超过一个指针字（pointer-word）长。
We're, when we refer to word sign, we're saying 64 bits,
当我们说字（word）时，是 64 位，
so if we have something that is twice the size of a pointer-word,
所以如果我们有两倍于指针字大小的东西，
we can put that in a register pair
我们可以把它放入寄存器对中，
and so the same convention holds true for return addresses
因此同样的约定也适用于返回地址，
where if we have something that's the size of twice pointer-word,
如果我们有一个指针字两倍大小的东西，
we can stick that in a0 and a1 and use that as the return address,
可以把它放在 a0 和 a1 中，并作为返回地址。
I think you'll run into problems if you only try to put something in a1.
我想如果你只往 a1 里写入，可能会遇到问题。
Makes sense, thanks.
理解了，谢谢。
Why are the registers not like continuous,
为什么寄存器不是连续的，
so why is like a0 and one separate from?
为什么 a0 和 a1 是分开的？
Sorry no that's a bad example,
抱歉，这不是一个好例子，
that's why is s1 separate from s2,
为什么 s1 和 s2 是分开的，
why the a in between like is there any point in that.
为什么 a 在它们中间，这有什么意义吗？
Yeah, so, I mentioned this briefly earlier,
是的，我之前提到，
but there is a compressed, this is a guess I don't I don't know for sure,
这只是一个猜测，我不是很确定，
but there's a compressed version of the RISC-V instructions
有一个压缩版本的 RISC-V 指令，
which are 16 bits in size as opposed to 64.
它的大小是 16 位，而不是 64 位。
And you would use that to try to make your code takes less space in memory,
你可以用它来使代码在内存中占用更少的空间，
and when you use those 16 bit instructions, you only have accesses to registers 8 through 15,
当你使用 16 位指令时，只能访问寄存器 8 到 15 位，
so I think s1 is separate from s2 to eleven,
所以我认为 s1 与 s2 到 s11 分开，
because they want to make it clear,
是因为他们想要明确，
that s1 is available to you in the compressed instruction mode, whereas two to eleven aren't.
s1 在压缩指令模式下可用，而 s2 到 s11 则不可用。
And the reason you know I don't know why they picked x, x8 to 15,
我不知道他们为什么选择 x ， x8 到 x15 ，
but I suspect that just looked at a bunch of code
但我相信，只要看一些代码，
and we're like these are the most commonly used registers.
就会发现这些是最常用的寄存器。
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
I had a question.
我有一个问题。
Besides the frame pointer, the stack pointer at all,
除了帧指针、栈指针，
I don't know why we would need more callee saved registers.
我不知道为什么我们需要更多的被调用者保存寄存器。
But we do have like a bunch of them.
但我们确实有很多这样的寄存器。
Yeah, the s1 to elevens those are just for,
是的， s1 到 s11 只是为了，
I believe use their freedom for the compiler or the programmer to use,
我相信只是为了让编译器或程序员有使用它们的自由，
so there may be there are certain cases where you want,
在某些情况下，你可能想要，
you want to guarantee that something is still around after after your function,
想要保证在函数之后仍然有一些东西存在
call the compiler can choose to use s1 to eleven to do that.
可以调用编译器选择使用 s1 到 s11 来做。
Um, I don't have like on hand, a specific example of where that's useful,
嗯，我现在没有一个具体的例子来说明，
but, I'm sure it shows up,
但是，我肯定它会出现的，
where having a callee saved value is important.
具有被调用者保存值是很重要的。
But these are basically basically a programmer or compiler's choice to use s1 to eleven.
这些基本上是程序员或编译器选择使用 s1 到 s11 。
I should note that these floating point registers their floating point, arithmetic,
我要提醒一下，这些浮点寄存器，浮点算数，
as far as I'm aware, you won't see them in this class,
据我所知，你们在这节课上不会看到它们，
and so you don't really need to worry about them.
所以不需要担心它们。
Okay, so we started talking a little bit about function calls,
好的，我们开始讨论一下函数调用，
and so with that I want to move us into discussion of the stack.
有了这些，我想开始讨论堆栈。
So this is This is we're talking about the stack,
这就是我们要讨论的堆栈，
and the stacked, if you've seen it like before,
堆栈，就像你以前看到的那样，
the reason why the stack is important is
它之所以重要是因为，
it's what keeps our functions organized and sane,
它使函数保持组织和正常运行，
and it's what allows what makes functions work, it's what makes return work
它允许函数工作，允许函数返回，
and it's also where often we will find ourselves saving our registers and things like that.
这也是我们经常编写保存寄存器之类的代码。
Um.
嗯。
So, here, I've given just a pretty simple layout of what the stack looks like,
在这里，我给出了堆栈的一个非常简单的布局，
and so each of these boxes here is what we refer to as a stack frame.
而且这里的每个框都是我们所说的栈帧。
And every time we get, which are generated by function calls.
每次我们得到栈帧，都是由函数调用生成的。
Every time we call a function
每次我们调用一个函数，
that function makes for itself its own stack frame
该函数都会为自己创建栈帧，
and which it uses itself and does that by moving around the stack pointer,
并通过移动栈指针来使用它，
so here's the stack pointer,
这个是栈指针，
and this is it's very important to remember.
记住这些是很重要的。
With stacks, we start from high addresses and we grow downwards. Too low addresses,
对于栈，我们从高地址开始，然后向下扩展到低地址，
so the stack grows down always.
所以栈总是向下扩展。
And so you'll see that the arithmetic for stack pointer is usually done via subtraction,
所以你会看到栈指针的运算通常是通过减法来完成的，
we want to make a new stack frame in assemblies,
我们要在汇编中创建一个新的栈帧，
the stack grows downwards.
栈就向下扩展。
And stack frames for function contain I see registers local variables,
函数栈帧包含寄存器、局部变量，
also like I was saying,
就像我说的，
if you run out of argument registers additional arguments will show up on the stack,
如果参数寄存器用完了，额外的参数就会出现在栈上，
and so not as stack frames are not all the same size,
栈帧不一定是相同大小，
even though they are in this diagram, that's not the case,
尽管在这张图中它们是相同的，但事实并非如此，
different functions have different numbers of local variables
不同函数具有不同数量的局部变量，
different registers so on and so forth,
不同的寄存器等，
and so stack frames will be different sizes.
因此栈帧具有不同的大小，
But the two things that you can definitely count on,
但是有两件事是可以确定的，
which are important is that the return address will always be on the first thing
这很重要，返回地址总是在第一个，
and the frame pointer, the previous frames frame pointer
并且，帧指针，前一帧帧指针
is also going to show up on the stack at a predictable location,
也会出现在栈中可预测位置，
so the two important registers here are sp,
两个重要的寄存器，这个是 sp ，
which you know as we discussed is used for, this is the bottom of the stack.
正如我们讨论的，这是栈的底部。
Or generally you know it's the location of the stack,
或者说是栈所在的位置，
and then fp is are also important register and this points to the top of current frame.
fp 也是重要的寄存器，指向当前帧的顶部。
And this is important,
这一点很重要，
because that means that the return address and the previous fp
因为这意味着返回地址和前一 fp
will always be at a fixed location from the current frame pointer.
将始终位于当前帧指针的固定位置。
So that means that if I want to find my return address
这意味着如果我想找到返回地址，
or I want to find the previous frame,
或者想找到上一帧，
I can always get to those values by looking at the current frame pointer
我总是可以通过查看当前帧指针来获得这些值，
and the reason why we store the previous frame pointer is
我们之所以存储前一个帧指针，
to allow us to jump back,
是为了可以向后跳转，
so once this function returns we can move this into fp
一旦这个函数返回，我们可以把它移动到 fp ，
and all of a sudden
然后，
fp again will go from pointing to this, this stack frame, to now pointing to this stack frame.
fp 从指向这个栈帧，到指向这个栈帧。
So we use the frame pointer to manipulate our stack frames
所以，我们使用帧指针来操作栈帧，
and make sure we're always going to one corresponding to the correct function.
并确保始终指向函数对应的栈帧。
And that's that's kind of how things how things are done
这就是栈的工作方式，
and the these pieces of the stack need to be created by assembly
栈的这部分是使用汇编语言实现的，
and so everything's everything in that calling conventions document that you read about
你读到的调用约定文档中的所有内容，
that's all enforced by effectively by the compiler,
都是由编译器实施的，
so the compiler adheres to the calling convention and it's what generates the stack frame,
编译器遵循调用约定，生成栈帧，
it generates the assembly code that makes our stack frames look correct,
生成汇编代码，保证栈帧正确，
so often at the top of a function, you'll see what's called a function prologue.
所以通常在函数的开头，你会看到所谓的函数序言。
And then there will be the body of the function
然后是函数体，
and then there will be an epilogue that shows up after that,
然后是一个函数尾声。
so this is kind of like, when an assembly function will often look like.
这就是汇编函数通常看起来的样子，
And we'll take a look at,
我们现在来看一下，
now, so here I have another function sum_then_double,
这里我有另一个函数 sum_then_double ，
so you'll note that [] that sum_to not have any of these things
注意， sum_to 没有这些东西，
that it it should if it was a proper function
一个真正的函数应该有的，
and this works fine because it's simple enough,
它也是可用的，因为足够简单，
so it does all of its computations on a0
它的所有计算都是在 a0 上进行的，
and so things are, things are good and we're also not it's a it's a leaf function,
所以是好的，我们把它称为叶子函数，
so, you'll see if you've seen the term leaf function
如果你看到叶子函数这个术语，
that's a function that doesn't call another function,
它是一个不调用另一个函数的函数，
and the functions are special in that
这种函数的特殊之处是，
they don't need to worry about saving their own return address
它们不需要考虑保存自己的返回地址，
or saving really any of the caller saved registers.
或者保存任何调用者保存寄存器。
Because they're going to they're not going to make another function call,
因为它们不会进行另一个函数调用，
so they don't have to be as careful,
所以它们不需要那么小心。
sum_then_double on the other hand is not a leaf function,
另一方面， sum_then_double 不是叶子函数，
so you can see here, it calls sum_to.
你可以在这里看到，它调用了 sum_to 。
And so it does need to include that that prologue,
所以它需要包含函数序言，
and so we see here that we are subtracting 16 from the stack pointer,
这里我们可以看到，从栈指针减去 16 ，
so we're making space on our stack,
我们在栈上腾出空间，
we're storing the return address for sum_then_double on the stack,
我们将 sum_then_double 的返回地址存储在栈中，
and then we make our call to sum_to,
然后调用 sum_to ，
and after that all this function does is it calls sum_to
在此之后，函数所做的全部工作就是调用 sum_to 。
and then doubles the result, doubles the result turn by sum_to,
然后将 sum_to 返回的结果加倍，
and here you can see the epilogue,
这里你可以看到函数尾声，
so we load the return address back in to ra
我们将返回地址加载回 ra ，
and delete our stack frame and then jump out of the function.
并删除栈帧，然后跳出函数。
And so we can run that to make sure it does what we would expect.
我们可以运行它来确保达到预期的效果。
Go here.
在这里。
We can run, so if we run demo2 or demo1
我们可以运行，如果我们运行 demo1 ，
we got the result of fifteen for the sum,
我们得到了总和为 15 的结果，
and I'll tell you that demo2 just, just call sum_then_double
我会演示 demo2 ，调用 sum_then_double ，
and indeed you know it happily doubles the sum returned by sum_to.
它就是把 sum_to 返回的结果加倍。
And so a question I have for anybody
所以我有一个问题，
what happens if we delete this prologue and epilogue,
如果我们删除这个函数序言和函数尾声，会发生什么，
what happens if we just have this as our function, sum_then_double.
如果我们在 sum_then_double 这样操作，会发生什么。
Can anybody predict what's going to happen.
有人能预测会发生什么吗？
I mean one thing is that sum_then_double wouldn't know the return address that it should return to,
我的意思是， sum_then_double 不知道它应该返回的返回地址，
so upon calling sum_to, that's going to override the return address to be sum_then_double's,
因此，在调用 sum_to 时，将覆盖 sum_then_double 的返回地址，
at the end of sum_then_double, it's not going to return to its original caller.
在 sum_then_double 的末尾，它不会返回到最初的调用者。
Yeah exactly and we can see that that's what happens.
是的，没错。我们可以看看发生了什么。
Again, so if we exit out of this and exit out of this
我们退出这个，退出这个，
and we re-compile with now with our broken function.
我们现在用损坏的函数重新编译。
We can take a look at exactly what's gonna happen,
我们可以看看到底会发生什么，
so we can actually set our break point for sum_then_double.
我们可以在 sum_then_double 设置中断，
And set up tui and let it continue,
设置 tui 并让它继续运行，
so we now run demo2,
现在我们运行 demo2 ，
okay we're at sum_then_double.
好的，我们在 sum_then_double 。
And again, this is an assembly only function,
同样的，这里只有一个汇编函数，
so we're going to want to look at it in assembly,
所以我们在汇编中查看它，
so we'll do layout asm layout reg,
我们输入 layout asm ， layout reg ，
because it's important what's in the registers in this case.
因为这种情况下，寄存器的内容也很重要。
And you'll see that gdb knows a whole bunch of extra information
你将看到 gdb 中有很多信息，
and so we can see that, you can see that,
我们可以看到，
ra currently, so the return address, currently points to demo2 the plus eighteen,
ra 当前，返回地址指向 demo2 加 18 ，
so, it points effectively into the function demo2.
这表示进入函数 demo2 。
And now we can run,
现在我们可以运行，
we can just kind of step through our function and see what happens.
我们可以单步检查函数，看看会发生什么。
We've called sum_to
我们调用了 sum_to ，
and immediately we can see that the return address was overwritten by sum_to,
可以看到返回地址被 sum_to 覆盖，
to now point to sum_then_double plus four,
现在指向 sum_then_double 加 4 ，
which makes sense, you know that's what we expect,
这是对的，就是我们期望的。
if we go back into our code,
如果返回我们的代码，
we call sum_to and so sum_to should return to here.
调用 sum_to ， sum_to 应该返回到这里。
And now we can step through you know so on up
现在我们可以单步，
and then we get back into.
然后我们再回到。
Oops, the wrong s.
糟糕，出错了。
Okay, so now we're here
好的，我们现在在这里，
and now when sum_then_double returns as exactly as Amir pointed out
当 sum_then_double 返回时，就像 Amir 说的，
its return, it has not restored its own return address
它没有恢复自己的返回地址，
and instead its return address is still the one that was used by sum_to,
而是它的返回地址仍然是 sum_to 使用的，
and so we will get into an infinite loop
所以我们会进入一个无限循环，
where we just keep doing this over and over and over again
一遍又一遍地重复这个过程，
and we'll never terminate from it.
永远不会结束。
And so this is I think this is a good illustration of
我想这很好地说明了，
why it's important to keep track of our caller versus callee saved registers
为什么跟踪调用者保存和被调用者保存寄存器很重要，
and hopefully this also shows
这也展示了
that you can use kind of gdb to debug these sorts of these sorts of problems,
可以使用 gdb 来调试这类问题，
so let's restore what we had.
让我们恢复之前的代码。
I will go into some other demos to talk about to illustrate.
我将使用其他一些演示代码来讲解。
Somebody ask why are we subtracting 16.
有人问，我们为什么要减去 16 ？
That's to put space to get our stack frame,
这是为了给栈帧腾出空间，
so this is subtracting 16 from the stack pointer,
所以从栈指针中减去 16 ,
so it's moving it down basically in memory.
它在内存中向下移动。
Moving it down so that we now have space for our own stack frame,
将其向下移动，以便我们有空间容纳自己的栈帧，
then we can stick stuff there.
然后我们就可以把东西放在那里。
So because at this point, in fact that we don't want to override what's at the stack pointer,
因为这时候，我们不想覆盖栈指针上的东西，
why not 4 I is just well 4,
为什么不是 4 ，
we need to do 16 because instructions are 64.
我们需要 16 ，因为指令是 64 位。
Yeah I guess I guess we wouldn't don't actually need to do 16,
是的，我想实际上不一定需要 16 ，
but that's generally what you'll see generally just see,
但通常你会看到，
I don't think yeah you, you can't you can't do 4 because you need 8.
我想不能使用 4 ，因为需要 8 ，
So 4 doesn't work, but I think you could do the instruction size,
不能使用 4 ，但我想你可以使用指令大小，
and the size of the register registers are 64,
而寄存器大小是 64 位，
yeah, and then so the convention why you usually see 16 is because
那么为什么通常看到 16 是因为，
if we jump back to our document, usually we have the return address and the frame pointer,
如果我们回到文档，通常有返回地址和帧指针，
we're not doing that here because or being [not super careful] with our assembly.
我们在这里不这样做，因为不是非常小心地处理我们的汇编。
So normally, if we if we look in,
所以通常情况下，如果我们看内部，
I'm sure,
我肯定，
if we look in kernel at this and we'll see.
如果我们看内核，就会明白这一点。
Yeah, so we look in kernel data we see it's also 16,
我们查看内核数据，发现它也是 16 ，
this is generally what you'll see with the compiler.
这通常是编译器处理后看到的。
Um, OK, so now we can.
好的，现在我们可以。
After this.
在这之后。
We fix our function and now we can look at some C code.
我们修复函数，现在看一些 C 代码。
Alright, so here we have demo4
好的，现在我们有 demo4 ，
which is just basically, a copy of main function,
它基本上就是 main 函数的复制，
like a imitation of the main function,
是对 main 函数的模拟，
so we have our args, which is an array of strings
我们有 args ，它是一个字符串数组，
and we have dummymain
我们有 dummymain ，
which takes a number of arguments and the arguments string
它接收一些参数和参数字符串，
and just print it out, for us.
然后打印出来。
And so that's all that's that's all that's happening here is pretty straightforward,
这就是所有的，都很简单，
if we set a break point in dummymain,
如果我们在 dummymain 中设置断点，
then hop over, let.
然后跳过来。
Okay, we'll just continue and we start this run demo4,
好的，我们继续，运行 demo4 ，
okay so we now we hit dummymain.
现在我们到了 dummymain 。
And there's a couple of important things to remember about,
有几件重要的事要记住，
that you can use gdb for regarding stack frames,
你可以使用 gdb 来显示栈帧，
so if we type i so again, that's info,
我们输入 i ，也就是 info ，
if we type i frame, we can see a whole bunch of useful information about the current stack frame,
如果我们输入 i frame ，可以看到很多关于当前栈帧的信息，
so we can see we're at stack level zero,
可以看到，我们在栈级别 0 ，
level zero means it's [] is down in the call stack
级别 0 意味着它[]在调用栈下面，
that we can go and the frame is at this address.
我们可以转到，而且帧在这个地址。
The program counter which is okay, that's all well and good,
程序计数器也没问题，一切都很好，
we have a saved program counter as well,
我们也有一个保存的程序计数器，
and if we again if we take this address and we jump into kernel.asm.
如果我们使用这个地址跳转到 kernel.asm 。
We search for that address,
我们搜索那个地址，
we can indeed that that addresses inside of inside of demo4,
我们可以在 demo4 中找到那个地址，
which is exactly where we expect the program to return to
这正是我们希望程序返回的地址，
and it was called by a frame at this address
它是由这个地址的帧调用的，
source language C,
源代码 C ，
that's that's nice to know
很高兴知道这一点，
and then we have the argument list also starts this address,
然后我们有参数列表，也是从这个地址开始的，
of course, in this case, we have most of our arguments in registers
当然，本例中我们的大部分参数都在寄存器中，
and then we can even see what args are,
我们甚至可以看到 args 是什么，
we argc is three and argv is this address.
argc 是 3 ， argv 是这个地址。
And if we want a more in-depth examine things
如果我们想要更深入研究一些东西，
we can look at things like info args,
可以使用 info args 命令，
which will tell us information about the arguments to the function, we can look at,
它告诉我们有关函数参数的信息，我们可以查看，
but more importantly we can type we type backtrace or bt works as well,
但更重要的是，我们可以输入 backtrace 或 bt ，
we get a full backtrace of all of the stacks,
我们得到了整个栈帧的 backtrace ，
all of the stack frames from the call stack,
调用栈中的所有栈帧，
so you can see something questionable happen here,
你可以在这里看到一些问题，
that's when we invoke a system call,
当我们调用系统调用时，
then we get to the usertrap function,
然后我们到达 usertrap 函数，
then to the syscall function,
然后是 syscall 函数，
then to sys_demo then to demo4.
然后是 sys_demo ，然后是 demo4 。
And then finally to dummymain
然后转到 dummymain ，
and if we want to investigate any of these stack frames more in-depth,
如果我们想更深入研究这些栈中的一个，
we can do frame and then whatever number is along the side here,
我们可以使用 frame 再加上一个数字，
so let's say I want to look at what was my stack frame when syscall called,
比如我想看看当 syscall 调用时栈帧是什么，
I can go to frame three,
我可以查看第 3 帧，
and so now, inside of gdb, I'm looking at that stack frame,
现在，在 gdb 里面，我正在查看栈帧，
so I type info frame I can get this.
我输入 info frame ，可以得到这个。
And here we get a lot more a lot more information
这里我们得到了更多信息，
we have a bunch of saves registers.
有很多保存寄存器。
Um, we have some local variables,
我们有一些局部变量，
we don't have any arguments to this function,
这个函数没有任何参数，
we can see where the program counter were supposed to jump back to,
我们可看到程序计数器应该跳回到哪里，
all kinds of things like that,
诸如此类的东西，
so this is super super useful for if you're debugging things,
所以，如果你在调试东西，这是非常有用的。
and in fact it's so useful,
事实上，它非常有用，
we make you implement your own version, nowhere near as in depth as what gdb tells you,
我们让你自己实现的版本，远不如 gdb 告诉你的那样深入。
but we're one of the exercises on the next lab
我们在下一个实验中的练习之一，
will be to implement your own backtrace helper function,
是实现你自己的 backtrace helper 函数，
for use when debugging things inside the lab.
以便在实验内调试时使用。
And so back backtrace is quite useful,
因此 backtrace 非常有用，
and then if we type frame zero, we go back to where we were supposed to be.
如果我们输入 frame 0 ，就会返回到刚才的位置。
And if we want to investigate,
如果我们想要调查，
you probably noticed it's not super helpful,
你可能注意到这不是很有帮助，
you know argv is a string as an array of strings
argv 是字符串数组形式的字符串，
and so we just got a ref, we just get an address,
而且我们只拿到了地址，
for where that's actually stored and if we want to look at what's in there,
如果我们想看看地址里面是什么，
there's a couple ways of doing this,
有几种方法可以做到，
the easiest is if we type print, p is for print,
最简单的是，输入 print ， p 表示打印，
and then if we dereference the address,
然后我们间接引用该地址，
so we go look at what's at address,
我们看看地址那里是什么，
we do that and,
我们这样做，
you know, as you would expect, we get the first element of that array,
你知道，正如预期的，我们得到了该数组的第一个元素，
because when it tries to print a string,
因为当它试图打印字符串时，
it'll go as C says, it'll go until it hits the null character,
就像 C 语言里，它会一直运行，直到遇到空字符，
so we get foo which is the first element in that array,
所以我们得到 foo ，它是数组中的第一个元素，
and if we want to get more things we can put in the length,
如果我们想要得到更多，可以加上一个长度，
so if we do @ then a number,
如果我们输入 @ ，然后一个数字，
it'll go up to a certain index,
它会上升到某个索引，
so then we can see both of the strings here
然后我们可以看到这两个字符串，
and again gdb is quite smart,
同样， gdb 非常聪明，
so we can even use argc to print out the whole argument array.
我们甚至可以用 argc 打印整个参数数组。
And so all of that information is available to you,
所有的信息对你来说都是可用的，
you, however you want to get it, so gdb the superpower tool.
不管你想得到什么， gdb 是很有用的工具。
Why does gdb sorry,
为什么 gdb ，不好意思，
why does the compiler sometimes optimize out argc and argv,
为什么编译器有时候会优化 argc 和 argv ，
that has happened to be before.
之前发生过这样的事。
Yeah that just means that the compiler found a more efficient way,
这意味着编译器找到了一种更有效的方法，
likely it just got rid of the variable and it's doing all of its operations,
很可能只是去掉了变量，并进行所有操作，
directly you know [] register might be doing all of its operations on a0,
你知道[]寄存器可能在 a0 上执行所有操作，
for example, it might just be doing all the computations on the return address.
比如，它可能只是对返回地址进行所有计算。
It's pretty common to see something like that,
这很常见，
if you if it's a variable that's not you know a hundred percent necessary.
如果它是一个非必须的变量。
If you know we don't let we don't give you control over the compiler,
我们不能控制编译器，
but if you ever find that in your day-to-day,
但是如果你在平时发现这个，
you can try setting the optimization flag for the compiler to zero,
你可以尝试将编译器的优化标志设置为零，
but even then you know the compiler will do will do it, we'll do some level of optimization.
但即使这样，编译器仍会做一定程度的优化。
Bibic your hand is raised.
Bibic 你举手了。
Yeah what's the address, besides that $1 or $2 you know like before foo or bar.
是的，在 $1 和 $2 后面的地址是什么，就是在 foo 或 bar 之前的，
Dollar, this?
美元符号，你说这个吗？
Yeah, so what's that address is that the address where foo is.
是的，那个地址就是 foo 所在的地址。
Probably yes.
可能是吧。
But then argv points to some other address shouldn't those be the same.
但是，然后 argv 指向其他地址，它们不应该是相同的。
So argv is on this stack,
所以 argv 在这个栈上，
and you know, so the reason why, if you look at these addresses,
如果你看这些地址，
we can see that they're in the kernel, just by the 8000.
我们可以看到它们在内核中，就在 8000 。
Um, which makes sense because we declared statically right,
这是有道理的，因为我们静态声明，
so in demos, if I go here they're declared here.
所以在示例程序中，如果我走到这里，它们会在这里声明。
And so they're basically they're sitting somewhere in the kernel
所以它们位于内核的某个地方，
and they're all [] stars argc or argv is an array of [] stars
它们都是星号标记的， argc 或 argv 是一系列的间接引用，
and so I imagined each element points to points to its own string right,
所以我想每个元素都指向自己的字符串，
so it's an array of pointers.
它是一个指针数组。
I see.
我明白了。
[]
[]
I also have a question about this,
我也有一个问题，
the $3 version of the array has
$3 版本的数组具有，
if I look at these addresses
如果看这些地址，
the first one is suffixed by 38,
第一个后缀是 38 ，
the second one is suffixed by 40
第二个后缀是 40 ，
and the third one is 48.
第三个是 48 。
Which is not uniform, even though the length of each of the three arguments is three,
这不是统一的，虽然三个参数的长度都是三个，
so why, why are they different.
所以为什么它们是不同的。
Um, not in I'm not a hundred percent certain,
嗯，我也不是百分百确定，
my guess is that this is an attempt to align things.
我猜是为了对齐数据。
Um, right, so to get them on a reasonable alignment,
让它们保持合理的位置，
it is uniform in hex as, people are pointing out.
有人指出它们用十六进制表示是对齐的。
Oh yeah, yeah yeah see it now right, thanks.
好的，理解了，谢谢。
So you'll sometimes see where strange things are laid out strangely
所以有时候你看到东西放在那里很奇怪，
where there might be two things as strange offsets
可能是两个东西有不同的偏移量，
and that's just because not everything is naturally the same sized.
因为并不是所有的东西都是相同大小的。
Okay, any other questions.
好的，还有其他问题吗？
Okay, we can skip the fifth demo.
好的，我们可以跳过第五个 demo 。
And so another useful function that we get from gdb,
gdb 的另一个有用的功能是，
instead of just break points, they're also watch points
不仅有断点，还有观察点，
and we can also set a conditional break points.
并且我们还可以设置有条件的断点。
So, I'll just briefly go over that.
我简单介绍一下。
Run demo6 so we can set inside this function,
运行 demo6 以便我们可以在函数中设置，
we can watch so we can set a watch point,
我们可以设置观察点，
I think here you'll see.
我想在这里你可以看到。
Yeah, so here you'll see what Luke was talking about where we see that some has been optimized out,
向 Luke 所说的，一些东西被优化了，
likely because it's just being a zero or something.
可能是因为它只是零或别的什么。
We can look even at the assembly for this right,
我们可以看一下这个汇编，
so we can layout split.
我们可以使用 layout split 。
And indeed, we can see that all just being, It's all just being done on the stack,
事实上，可以看到所有都是在栈上完成的，
it looks like to me.
在我看来。
Oh, no, it's always been done in s0 s0 one three,
不，这都是在 s0, s0 1 3 上做的，
so here you can see the, compiler decided even to use the callee saved registers
在这里你可以看到，编译器使用的是被调用者保存寄存器，
and so we can set things like we do watch on i.
这样我们可以设置，对 i 进行观察。
Alright we haven't declared i,
好的，我们还没有声明 i ，
yet because we're not inside we're not inside the for loop.
因为我们不在循环里面，
So we step through the C instructions,
所以我们单步执行 C 代码，
now if we do information for the locals, we see we get i,
现在我们对本地变量查看信息，会看到 i ，
we can even watch watch point on sum.
我们甚至可以在 sum 设置观察点。
So now anytime that sum changes will actually get a notification,
现在任何时候 sum 改变都会收到通知，
so we can continue and then we'll get a delete here,
我们继续，然后这里有一个删除，
because some has been moved so we can't we can't actually watch it,
因为有东西被删除了，所以我们不能查看它，
we can even do things like break point on sum_to,
我们甚至可以做一些事情，比如在 sum_to 上设置断点，
so this is a conditional break point if, well, let's actually see was i currently, so i currently 1,
这是一个条件断点，如果 i 现在是 1 ，
let's say I think my loop is breaking and whenever i is 5,
比如，让循环在 i 是 5 的时候中断，
well if I want to specifically debug that case,
如果我想专门调试这种情况，
I can set a break point on sum_to if i equal 5.
我可以在 sum_to 上设置一个断点，如果 i 等于 5 。
So now we have this break point, and if we continue along,
现在我们有了这个断点，如果我们继续
we'll get to sum_to, and we can see that it actually printed out the first couple values
我们得到 sum_to ，可以看到它打印了第一组值，
and so we only break now on sum_to if if i if we hit that break point condition.
现在我们只在 i 符合条件时在 sum_to 上中断。
And so that's, it can be again can be useful if you want to debug specific edge cases of your code
也就是说，如果你要调试代码特定的边界条件，它会很有用，
and watch points can be useful
观察点可能会很有用，
if for instance you think that something shouldn't be changing, but you suspect that it is
如果你认为某些东西不应该改变，但你怀疑它改变了，
or you think that something is going wrong every time you change a certain variable.
或者你认为每次你改变某个变量都会出问题。
And so that's that's a it's one one usage for that.
这是它的一种用法。
And the last thing I want to talk about today is struct,
今天，我最后要说的是结构体（struct），
struct pretty important, they'll come up in in the labs often
结构体非常重要，它会经常出现在实验里，
and also.
还有。
So, what as, I'll talk a little bit about the way structs are laid out in memory.
所以我会简单介绍一下结构体在内存中的布局。
And so a structure is basically it's a continued contiguous area of memory,
基本上，一个结构体就是一个连续的内存区域，
so if we have some structure.
所以如果我们有一些结构体。
And we have like field one field two field three.
我们有字段一，字段二，字段三。
When we make that struct
当我们创建该结构体时，
those fields are going to be align next to each other in memory,
在内存中，这些字段将挨着排在一起。
you can kind of think of this like an array,
你可以把它想象成一个数组，
but f1 f2 f3 can all be different types.
但是 f1 f2 f3 可以是不同的类型。
And, we can pass them [] functions,
而且，我们可以把它们传递给函数，
usually they pass them as arguments to functions, usually they pass by reference,
它们作为参数传递给函数，通常是通过引用，
so here I've made a struct person with two integer arguments,
这里有一个结构体 person ，包含两个整型参数，
and I'm passing them, passing a person as an argument person
我传递一个 person 作为参数，
and printing out some of that information,
并打印出其中的一些信息，
so if we hop into gdb
如果我们进入 gdb ，
and let's delete all our break points and watch points,
让我们删除所有的断点和观察点，
and now we can set a break point at printPerson,
现在我们在 printPerson 上设置一个断点，
and it's continue and run seventh demo.
继续，并运行第七个 demo 。
We can see that now we're here and so if we type i frame,
现在可以看到，我们在这里，如果输入 i frame ，
we can see that we have an argument p.
我们可以看到，我们有一个参数 p 。
And indeed, we can see if we do print p,
事实上，如果我们打印 p ，
If we can even tell that it's struct person at this address
甚至能辨别出这个地址是 struct person ，
and we can if we dereference it,
我们可以间接引用它，
gdb will tell us exactly what p looks like it has id 1215 age 22.
gdb 告诉我们 p 的 id 是 1215 ， age 是 22 。
And just to show kind of how things are laid out.
只是展示一下结构提是怎么存放的。
You can take this address and we see at this address,
你可以取这个地址，我们可以在这个地址看到，
if we look. I remember exactly.
如果我们看。我记得很清楚。
Should be.
应该是的。
So if we again so we can use this to debug our structures.
如果我们再来一次，可以用这个来调试我们的结构体。
In in the code, we can take a look at what's going on with structures this way,
在代码中，我们可以看一下结构体是怎么回事，
so gdb is a super powerful tool
因此 gdb 是非常强大的工具，
not just for stepping through code,
不仅用于单步执行，
but also for examining all kinds of potentially problematic pieces in your code
还用于检查代码中各种类型的潜在问题。
and looking at arguments and stack frames and things like that,
而且可以查看参数和栈帧，
and this will be hopefully will be useful in the next lab,
这在下一个实验中很有用，
when you have to work with, with stack frames and with assembly code.
当你必须使用栈帧和汇编来编程时。
So that's that's mostly what I wanted to talk about today.
这就是我今天想讲的主要内容。
So, with the last kind of seven minutes of lecture,
最后还有 7 分钟，
I'll open it up to any any other questions you guys have.
你们可以提任何问题。
I had a bit of a tangential question,
我有一个离题的问题，
who is who manages the creation of compilers
谁管理从 C 到各种指令集架构
from to get from C to various instruction set architectures,
的编译器的创建，
is that the creator of the instruction set architecture, is the third parties like that.
是指令集架构的创建者，或是类似的但三方机构。
Um, I believe that it is not the creative the instruction set,
我想不是指令集的创建者，
so it's often a third party,
通常是第三方，
so the two big C compilers that you'll see
你们知道的的两个大的 C 编译器，
refer to GCC which is maintained by I think the GNU foundation
GCC 是由 GNU 基金会维护的，
and Clang llvm, which is its own thing,
Clang llvm 是自己维护的，
so I think you know you can find I believe llvm is even open source,
你可以发现， llvm 甚至是开源的，
so you can find. you can, you can find the code specifically that does this,
这样你就能找到，专门做这件事的代码。
when a new instruction set is released such as RISC-V,
当一个像 RISC-V 的新指令集发布时，
that calling convention document as well as all of those instruction documents,
调用约定文档以及所有这些指令文档一起发布，
I think carefully I assume
我猜，
there's a high level of cooperation between the compiler designer and the instruction set designer.
可能编译器设计者和指令集设计者之间有高级别的合作。
But yeah a short answer is I believe it's a third party who does it,
但简单来说，我相信是第三方维护的，
likely with a lot of cooperation from the people who make the instruction set.
很可能与指令集制作人员的大量合作。
RISC-V is probably, RISC-V might be an exception where because it came out of a research project,
RISC-V 可能是一个例外，因为它来自一个研究项目，
they may have written the compiler for it themselves, as well.
他们可能也自己编写了编译器。
I I don't think Intel has for example has input in in GCC or llvm.
我不认为英特尔在 GCC 或 llvm 上有所投入。
Other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
Okay, well, thanks for listening,
好的，感谢收听，
in that case I guess we can.
那样的话，我想我们可以。
You can end the lecture here,
你可以在这里结束，
a five minutes to spare, so have a nice rest.
还有 5 分钟，好好休息一下。